Register to The Papers of the Society for the Publication of American Music
Yale University Music Library
The Papers of the Society for the Publication of American Music
1924-1974
Misc. Ms. 172
Yale University Music Library
2
(5 boxes)
Correspondence and other documents from the Society for the Publication of American Music (SPAM)
Society for the Publication of American Music
Conditions Governing Access
The Papers are open to researchers by appointment. There are no restricted materials in the collection. Please contact the Special Collections staff to schedule an appointment. Some of the materials may be stored at the Library's off-campus shelving facility, so researchers should allow at least two business days to have the appropriate boxes paged.
Arrangement
In 2 series as follows: I. Original Holdings. II. Later additions.
Scope and Contents
This collection documents the activities of the Society for the Publication of American Music from its inception in 1919 to its dissolution in May, 1969. The bulk of materials dates from the last 10 years of the Society's existence and consists of: correspondence; subscription records; royalty, bank, and other financial records; officers' notes; and a small number of programs and reviews.
Biographical / Historical
The Society for the Publication of American Music (SPAM) was founded in 1919 as a vehicle for relatively unknown contemporary composers to have their works published and then distributed to individual subscribers as well as university libraries. Each year, the board of directors examined numerous proposals and selected one or two works for publication.
Yale University figured prominently in the history of SPAM. At the time of SPAM's dissolution in 1969, Luther Noss, Dean of the School of Music, was the president, and Music Librarian Brooks Shepard was the treasurer. Many Yale composers were honored by SPAM, including Howard Boatwright, Jacob Druckman, Daniel Gregory Mason, Mel Powell, Quincy Porter, and David Stanley Smith.
Music publishing; Music -- United States -- 20th Century; Bailey, Parker, 1902-1982; Barzin, Leon, 1900-1999; Bassett, Leslie, 1923-2016; Bauer, Marion, 1882-1955; Bergsma, William, 1921-1994; Bezanson, Philip, 1916-1975; Blackwood, Easley, 1933-; Boatwright, Howard, 1918-1999; Brunswick, Mark, 1902-1971; Cole, Ulric, 1905-1992; Cone, Edward T., 1917-2004; Coolidge, Elizabeth Sprague, 1864-1953; Dahl, Ingolf, 1912-1970; Diamond, David, 1915-2005; Donato, Anthony, 1909-1990; Druckman, Jacob, 1928-1996; Engel, Lehman, 1910-1982; Feist, Leonard, 1910-1996; Fetler, Paul; Fine, Irving, 1914-1962; Finney, Ross Lee, 1906-1997; Foss, Lukas, 1922-2009; Gold, Ernest, 1921-1999; Heilman, William Clifford; Heller, James G. (James Gutheim), 1892-1971; Holden, David, 1911-1996; Hughes, Edwin, 1884-1965; Jacobi, Frederick, 1891-1952; James, Philip, 1890-1975; Korn, Richard, 1908-1981; Kortschak, Hugo, 1884-1957; Koutzen, Boris, 1901-1966; Kramer, A. Walter (Arthur Walter), 1890-1969; Kroll, William, 1901-1980; Lockwood, Normand, 1906-2002; Luening, Otto, 1900-1996; Mason, Daniel Gregory, 1873-1953; Moore, Douglas, 1893-1969; Morris, Harold, 1890-1964; Noss, Luther, 1907-1995; Overton, Hall, 1920-1972; Palmer, Robert, 1915-2010; Persichetti, Vincent, 1915-1987; Porter, Quincy, 1897-1966; Powell, Mel, 1923-1998; Reese, Gustave, 1899-1977; Reiser, Alois, 1887-1977; Robertson, Leroy J., 1896-1971; Rochberg, George, 1918-2005; Schwarz, Boris, 1906-1983; Sowerby, Leo, 1895-1968; Stein, Leon, 1910-2002; Stevens, Halsey, 1908-1989; Stoessel, Albert, 1894-1943; Thomson, Virgil, 1896-1989; Trimble, Lester, 1923-1986; Tuthill, Burnet, 1888-1982; Van Vactor, David, 1906-1994; Wagenaar, Bernard, 1894-1971; Ward, John Owen; Ward, Robert, 1917-2013; Widdoes, Lawrence, 1932-; Wilson, George Balch, 1927-; Wilson, Keith L. (Keith Leroy), 1916-2013; Carl Fischer Music; National Music Council (U.S.); Society for the Publication of American Music
- Original Holdings, Series I
  - Bank Statements, 1960-1964 (Box 1, Folder 1)
  - Bank Statements, 1964-1974 (Box 1, Folder 2)
  - Income Tax Returns, to 1970 (Box 1, Folder 3)
  - Treasurer's bills and requisitions, 1959-1967 (Box 1, Folder 4)
  - Membership purchase orders, 1964-1965 (Box 1, Folder 5)
  - Correspondence - Subscribers (Box 1, Folder 6)
  - List of publications and agents (Box 1, Folder 7)
  - Biographical sketches of SPAM composers (Box 1, Folder 8)
  - By-laws, form letters, forms (Box 1, Folder 9)
  - Meetings, Notices, and Minutes, 1924-1969 (Box 1, Folder 10)
  - Correspondence: National Music Council (Box 2, Folder 1)
  - Correspondence: SPAM composers (Box 2, Folder 2)
  - Miscellaneous correspondence, 1939-1959 (Box 2, Folder 3)
  - Miscellaneous correspondence, 1960-1962 (Box 2, Folder 4)
  - Miscellaneous correspondence, 1963-1965 (Box 2, Folder 5)
  - Miscellaneous correspondence, 1966-1970 (Box 2, Folder 6)
  - Correspondence: Carl Fischer, 1962 (Box 2, Folder 7)
  - Correspondence: Oxford University Press (Box 2, Folder 8)
  - Royalties and correspondence: ASCAP & Carl Fischer (Box 3, Folder 1)
  - Bulletins and correspondence: ASCAP (Box 3, Folder 2)
  - Correspondence: 1962 Theodore Presser Agreement (Box 3, Folder 3)
  - Correspondence: Theodore Presser, 1962-1968 (Box 3, Folder 4)
  - Royalties and correspondence: Theodore Presser (Box 3, Folder 5)
  - Correspondence: Theodore Presser - SPAM dissolution (Box 3, Folder 6)
  - SPAM: Officers notes (Box 3, Folder 7)
  - Programs, articles, and tickets (Box 3, Folder 8)
  - Miscellaneous scores (Box 3, Folder 9)
  - Embosser (Box 3, Folder 10)
  - Subscriber file (Box 4, Folder 1)
- Later Additions, Series II
  - Correspondence, 1947-1957; 17 items (Box 5, Folder 1)
  - Minutes, 1954-1957; 7 items (Box 5, Folder 2)
  - Lists of publications, 7 items (Box 5, Folder 3)
  - Voting proxies for meetings, 1954-1957; 95 items (Box 5, Folder 4)
  - Incorporation and by-laws, 1919-1955; 3 items (Box 5, Folder 5)
  - Contracts, 1920-1929; 20 items (Box 5, Folder 6)
  - Contracts, 1930-1936; 8 items (Box 5, Folder 7)
  - Contracts, 1940-1950; 31 items (Box 5, Folder 8)
  - Biographical sketches, 1925, ?; 9 items (Box 5, Folder 9)
  - Miscellaneous items, 1926-1954, ?; 22 items (Box 5, Folder 10)